Guide to the Mirecourt House Records, 1975-2019 UA.31.16.0003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mirecourt House records
1975-2001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Mirecourt House
UA.31.16.0003
0.5 Linear Feet
Contains the records of Mirecourt House, an independent, co-educational, social, selective undergraduate residence hall at Duke University. Types of materials include constitutions, rosters, correspondence, photographs, applications, surveys, newsletters, schedules, reports, clippings, poster, and color slides. Major subjects include student life, Duke University history, Delta Tau Delta fraternity, residential living, alcohol use, and governance of residential halls. Materials date from 1975 to 2019.
Access Restrictions
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Mirecourt House records were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1980, 1985-1986, and 2019.
Biographical/Historical note
Mirecourt House, established ca. 1975 is an independent co-educational, social-selective residence hall for Duke University undergraduate students in their junior and senior years. Some of Mirecourt House's programs have included a ropes course, tutoring at the Salvation Army, karaoke, and a variety of themed parties. Mirecourt is governed by a House Council elected by members of the group.
Mirecourt is located in Craven Quad of the West Campus of Duke University. In the 1970s, Mirecourt House was part of the Association of Independent Houses. In the 1980s, Mirecourt became part of the Edens Federation. The Edens Federation was established to represent interests of undergraduate residents of Duke University who lived on West Campus in Mirecourt House, Taylor House, Burton House, Lancaster House, Tabard House, and York House. In 1982, the Delta Tau Delta fraternity attempted to move in and fill three floors of the house, causing protest among house members.
Mirecourt House participates in Rush and attracts about 300-500 rushees to fill 10-30 spots. The house is currently co-ed and social-selective.
Scope and Contents note
Contains memos, correspondence, membership applications, clippings, evaluations, reports, minutes, photographs, social calendars, and a poster pertaining to the governance and social activities of Mirecourt House from 1975 to 2019. Also includes the Annual Reports of the Program of Coeducational Federations, Edens Federation newsletters, materials concerning a proposed takeover of the house's space by the Delta Tau Delta fraternity, common room signs from circa 2018-2019, and some color slides.
Related Material
Arts and Sciences Council records. Arts and Sciences Council. Residential Life Committee. Report, 1994
Duke University Archives.
Willimon. William H. "We Work Hard, We Play Hard:" A Report for the President, and the Provost, and the Vice President for Student Life of Duke University. (1993)
Duke University Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
Portions of this collection are closed except to the current president of Mirecourt House and members of Mirecourt House who have graduated from Duke.
Student housing -- North Carolina -- Durham; Residence and education; Dormitories -- North Carolina; College students -- Alcohol use -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University; Delta Tau Delta Fraternity
- Alcohol violations, 1999-2001 (Box 1)
  Access Restrictions
  This file may only be viewed by the President of Mirecourt House or by members of Mirecourt who have graduated.
- Annual reviews, 1992-2000 (Box 1)
- Applications of potential residents, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
- Applications of potential residents, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1980 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1975, 1983 (Box 1)
- Edens Federation, 1980-1982 (Box 1)
- Flyers, 2001 (Box 1)
- Governance, general, 1975-1986 (Box 1)
- House commitment survey, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
- Membership web, circa 2001 (Box 1)
- Minutes, house meetings, 1980 (Box 1)
- Mirecourt and Delta Tau Delta, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
- Party affairs, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
- Photographs, 2001 (Box 1)
- Rosters, 1995-2001 (Box 1)
- Social calendars and activities, 1992-1998 (Box 1)
- "Teams" poster, circa 1978-1979 (Box 1)
- Selected color slides, circa 1980-1981 (Box 1)
- Recruitment calendars, 2016, 2018 (Box 2)
- Photographs, circa 2018-2019 (Box 2)
- Common room signs, circa 2018-2019 (Box 2)